John Millet MD Papers
Oskar Diethelm Library
John Millet MD Papers
1928/1976
This collection contains the papers of John Millet, a psychiatrist and psychoanalyst who researched allergic disturbances, peripheral vascular disorders, and psychosomatic medicine. The collection has no series and needs to be reprocessed.
2.5 linear feet (6 boxes)
Millet, John A. P. (John Alfred Parsons), 1888-1976
Oskar Diethelm Library DeWitt Wallace Institute of Psychiatry: History, Policy and the Arts Weill Cornell Medical College 525 East 68th Street, Box 140 New York, NY 10065
1986.0001
Unknown.
This collection is open for research.
John Alfred Parsons Millet (1888-1976) was born to American parents in Broadway, Worcestershire, England and educated there until he came to the United States to attend Harvard College and Harvard Medical School, where he received his degrees in 1910 and 1914, respectively. After a medical internship at Peter Bent Brigham Hospital in Boston in 1916, he trained in psychotherapy at the Austen Riggs Center in 1930 and in psychoanalysis at the New York Psychoanalytic Institute in 1935.
In 1934, he and William B. Terhune established the Silver Hill Foundation for the treatment of psychoneuroses. With the help of Dr. Daniel Blain, Dr. Millet developed Tratelja Farms, Inc. in 1938 for the treatment of maladjustments, less serious emotional illnesses, and psychosomatic disorders. In 1939, he organized the Lake George Foundation with its treatment center at Diamond Point, New York and its all-purpose mental hygiene clinic in Glen Falls, New York. In 1946, he organized a neuropsychiatric consultation service for the American Rehabilitation Committee, Inc., later serving as chief of the panel of psychiatric consultants and president of the committee in 1972. Dr. Millet assisted in organizing the Third International Congress of Mental Health in London in 1946. He also assisted in the founding of the Rockland County Mental Health Association and the 1954 establishment of the county-sponsored center for mental health.
Dr. Millet was active in the American Academy of Psychoanalysis and was elected its fourth president in 1959-1960. In addition, he received the Academy's Distinguished Service Award in 1972. He aided in the establishment and administration of the New York School of Psychiatry, where he began as Associate Professor of Psychiatry and retried as Professor Emeritus after serving as Dean for five years from 1959 to 1964. He had many other involvements in academic psychiatry, including appointments of varying lengths from 1916 to the early 1970s at the University of Buffalo School of Medicine, the College of Physicians and Surgeons at Columbia University, the Columbia University Psychoanalytic Clinic for Training and Research, Cornell University Medical College, and Tulane University Medical School. In addition, he was affiliated with many branches of the New York State Society for Mental Health, the United Nations Consultative Committee on Mental Hygiene, and the United States Committee of the World Federation for Mental Health. Along with being a member of many societies of medicine, psychiatry, and psychoanalysis and a founding fellow of the American College of Psychoanalysis, he published extensively, as documented by the collection. Dr. Millet died in Nyack, New York, where he was in private practice, in 1976 at the age of eighty seven.
Millet, John A. P. (John Alfred Parsons), 1888-1976; Austen Riggs Center; American Psychoanalytic Association; Riggs, Austen Fox, 1876-1940; World Federation for Mental Health; Psychoanalysis; Psychosomatic medicine; New York Psychoanalytic Institute; Tratelja Farms; Terhune, William B. (William Barclay), 1893-1987; Blain, Daniel, 1898-1981; Silver Hill Hospital; Lake George Foundation; New York School of Psychiatry
This collection contains the papers of John Millet, a psychiatrist and psychoanalyst who researched allergic disturbances, peripheral vascular disorders, and psychosomatic medicine. The collection has no series and needs to be reprocessed.
- No series
  - Correspondence with Professor Leon Edel and others, 1974 - 1976 (Box 1)
  - Autobiographical manuscript, pages 3-123, Undated (Box 1)
  - Autobiographical manuscript, pages 124-251, Undated (Box 1)
  - Autobiographical manuscript, pages 252-377, Undated (Box 1)
  - Autobiographical manuscript, pages 378-521, Undated (Box 1)
  - Autobiographical manuscript, pages 522-643, Undated (Box 1)
  - Autobiographical manuscript, pages 644-723, Undated (Box 1)
  - Dr. Millet's copy of manuscript on Austen Fox Riggs, sample copy of thorough examination by Dr. Millet, and Dr. Millet's forward for book written by Dr. J. Rees, Undated (Box 2)
  - Material on Austen Riggs Center and correspondence with Otto A. Will Jr., Undated (Box 2)
  - Correspondence primarily with Dr. L. Kubie on Riggs, Undated (Box 2)
  - Austen Fox Riggs, Undated (Box 2)
  - History of the first ten years of the American Association of Psychoanalysis by Dr. Millet, Undated (Box 2)
  - Austen Fox Riggs correspondence and documents, including draft for biography of Austen Fox Riggs, 1942 - 1974; Undated (Box 2)
  - "The Academy in Perspective: Past, Present, and Future", Undated (Box 2)
  - "Psychoanalysis in the United States" manuscript, Undated (Box 2)
  - Introduction to Dr. W. Terhune's "History of the Silver Hill Foundation" manuscript, Undated (Box 2)
  - New York School of Psychiatry, Undated (Box 2)
  - Biographical material, including a list of publications, Undated (Box 3)
  - Unpublished papers, 1929 - 1956 (Box 3)
  - Unpublished papers, 1957 - 1967 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1974 - 1976 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1971 - 1975 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence with Silver Hill Foundation, 1967 - 1975 (Box 3)
  - Dr. Z.A. Liff's writings and Dr. Millet's comments, Undated (Box 3)
  - World Federation for Mental Health documents and correspondence, 1965 - 1974 (Box 3)
  - Writings, 1952 - 1972 (Box 4)
  - APA round tables manuscript, 1962 - 1964 (Box 4)
  - Discussions, 1938 - 1973 (Box 4)
  - "The Expanding Roles of the Psychiatrist and the Mental Health Hospital in Community Health" manuscript, 1965 (Box 4)
  - "Fatal Alcoholism with Premonitory Symptoms" manuscript, 1934 (Box 4)
  - Papers and discussions, 1952; 1955 (Box 4)
  - "Changing Faces of Psychoanalysis" manuscript, 1959 (Box 4)
  - Broadcasts, radio and TV, 1943 - 1966 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence on Francis Sedgwick and Mrs. J. van den Heuvel, 1975 (Box 4)
  - "What Price Psychosurgery?" manuscript, 1958 (Box 4)
  - "Report on Dreams in a Lifetime Struggle with Conscience" manuscript, 1962 (Box 4)
  - Book reviews, Undated (Box 4)
  - "Body, Mind, and Spirit" manuscript, 1950 (Box 4)
  - Program of and papers presented at the World Mental Health Assembly, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Report of the Ruth M. Knight Summer Theatre Workshop, 1970 (Box 5)
  - "The Place of the Medical Practitioner in the Selective Service System" manuscript, 1944 (Box 5)
  - Papers on sexual life in the later years, 1970 - 1972 (Box 5)
  - "Shock Therapies, Old and New" manuscript, 1957 (Box 5)
  - Manuscript of Dr. Millet's papers on dermatoses and Dr. Paul Gross' paper on psoriasis, 1946 (Box 5)
  - "The Spirit of Internationalism" manuscript, 1971 (Box 5)
  - "Time and Place for Everyone" manuscript, 1954 (Box 5)
  - "Theory and Training, a Travelogue" manuscript, 1973 (Box 5)
  - "Training for Community Mental Health Services" manuscript, 1964 (Box 5)
  - "On Tranquilizing Magic" manuscript, 1957 (Box 5)
  - Manuscript on childbearing, Undated (Box 5)
  - "Understanding the Emotional Aspects of Disability" manuscript, 1956 (Box 5)
  - Manuscript on understanding children, Undated (Box 5)
  - "Understanding the Patient and the Meaning to him of his Illness" manuscript, 1947 (Box 5)
  - "The Unfolding of Personality" manuscript, 1958 (Box 5)
  - "A Psychoanalyst's Viewpoint on Sexual Problems" manuscript, 1951 (Box 5)
  - "Psychoanalysis Americanus - Myth or Reality?" manuscript, 1960 (Box 5)
  - "Psychodynamic Approach to the Causes of the Civil War" manuscript, 1973 (Box 5)
  - "Psychological Problems of Authority" manuscript, 1960 (Box 5)
  - "Psychosomatic Medicine and the General Physician" manuscript, 1958 (Box 5)
  - "Relevances of Modern Ethology to Psychoanalysis" manuscript, 1967 (Box 5)
  - "Sigmund Freud and Pastoral Psychology" manuscript, 1956 (Box 5)
  - "The Future of Psychoanalysis" manuscript, 1971 (Box 5)
  - "The Future of Psychoanalysis in Psychiatric Practice" manuscript, 1966 (Box 5)
  - "The H-Ion Content of the Saliva in Neuroses and Other Pathological Conditions" working manuscript, 1928 (Box 5)
  - "Marriage, Terminable and Interminable" manuscript and discussion, 1965 (Box 5)
  - Reprints, Undated (Box 6)